Arriving in Morocco felt like a dream.
An oasis of peace, food and rest.
I remember being so happy. So proud. I’d crossed the Sahara, man! If I could do that, I could do anything.
It was wonderful to meet other travellers. There were all kinds of birds stopping in Morocco. Geese, cuckoos, swallows.
We came from all over Africa. We all had different reasons to be here; we would have never talked to each other before.
But the crossing had brought all us migrants together, suddenly making us feel like family.
And then, one day, in the middle of that menagerie, I met Banjoko.
The first time I saw him, I felt I was looking at myself in a pool of water. I was stunned.
Then I stepped closer, and so did he.
“Hi”, I said.
How could I explain this? I felt like I knew him.
When you meet birds from your own species far from home, you just click.
The world around is so unsettling, so unfamiliar, that you can feel an instant connection to total strangers.
“Hi Bird”, he replied.
“I’m Mawusi”, I said.
“Sweet. I’m Banjoko, but I got used to people calling me Bird. Nobody could pronounce my actual name.”
“So you already went to Europe, then?”
“I did, once, last spring. You’ll see, you’ll never be the same after that.
It’s hard to be in a place where nobody understands your name, where you are from or what you are.
Where nobody can tell whether you are a swallow, a sand martin or a willow warbler. To them it’s all the same, to them you are just another bird.”
I didn’t reply. He smiled.
“Don’t worry, there are good things too. And it’s easier when you travel in good company. So… would you like to join me, Bird?”